<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Chronologia sacra By the high ... Doctor Phil. Nicolai. lib. 2. de regno Christi. Shortly collected and augmented by Neils Michelsone. Cum priuilegio S. R. Maj. Newly translated out of the Germans and Dence tongue into English, by David Forbes. Pervsed, and accompanied with a short treatise and exhortation tending to repentance</title>
            <title>Chronologia sacra. English</title>
            <author>Nicolai, Philipp, 1556-1608.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1630</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 100 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 53 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08238</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18572</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S106265</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99841983</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99841983</idno>
            <idno type="VID">6606</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08238)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 6606)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 774:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Chronologia sacra By the high ... Doctor Phil. Nicolai. lib. 2. de regno Christi. Shortly collected and augmented by Neils Michelsone. Cum priuilegio S. R. Maj. Newly translated out of the Germans and Dence tongue into English, by David Forbes. Pervsed, and accompanied with a short treatise and exhortation tending to repentance</title>
                  <title>Chronologia sacra. English</title>
                  <author>Nicolai, Philipp, 1556-1608.</author>
                  <author>Michelsone, Neils, ed. and trans.</author>
                  <author>Forbes, David, of Edinburgh.</author>
                  <author>Arthus, Gotthard, b. 1568.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[112] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Iohn Wreittonn [sic],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Edinburgh :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1630.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Signatures: A-F G⁴ (-G4).</note>
                  <note>An edition of: Nicolai, Philipp.  Chronologia sacra.</note>
                  <note>Translated into German by Gotthard Arthus in 1598, into Danish by Niels Michelsone in 1628, and then into English by David Forbes.--NUC Pre-1956.</note>
                  <note>Title page mutilated, with some loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the National Library of Scotland.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible --  Chronology --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:6606:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6606:1"/>
            <p>CHRONOLOGIA SA<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>By the high <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Doctor</hi> PHIL. NICOLA <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>de regne Christi.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Shortly collected and augmented by <hi>Niels Michelſone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Privilegio S. R. Maj.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Newly tranſlated out of the <hi>German<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and <hi>Dence</hi> tongue into the <hi>Engliſh, By</hi> DAVID FORBES.</p>
            <p>Pervſed, and accompanied with a ſhort treatiſe and exhortation tending to repentance.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>MATH. Chap. 3. verſe. 2.</bibl>
               <p>Repent, for the Kingdome of Heaven is at hand.</p>
               <p>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>itae finem perpende, de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>raſtino haud vllus ſecurus.</p>
            </q>
            <p>EDINBVRGH Printed by <hi>Iohn Wreittoun,</hi> 1630.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:6606:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:6606:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOV<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ABLE, THE <hi>RIGHT RE<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>END AND</hi> WORTHY, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> LORD <hi>PRO<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>EST, BAILIFS</hi> MINI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>STERS, and remnant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ſelers <hi>of EDINBVRGH: All <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ſe</hi> of grace heere and glor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>heereafter,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>RIght Honourable, right Worthie, renowned Senat, and Paſtors:</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Finding my ſelfe ſomewhat bound vnto your benevolent fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours, therefore I in minde did decree to giue out the firſt fruits &amp; proofe of my labours, vnder the tuition and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence of your Honourable wiſedomes; and ſeeing I found this briefe and compendious <hi>German</hi> worke to bee fit for my purpoſe, eſpecially in thoſe tymes when men are moſt ſecure, &amp; ſleeping in worldly vanities, I was in a manner incited, through conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb facs="tcp:6606:3"/>
for to lay on my Talent, vnto the benefite of mine owne natiue Countrie, &amp; beeing obliged, for to approue that which I did publickly profeſſe, before your wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thie Senat, and within your renowned Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. Therefore I could ſee none more meete to dedicate the proofe of my labours, as vnto the conspicuous &amp; publicke cenſure of your Honourable Senat: Right Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, the Author of this little worke is a <hi>German</hi> Doctor in divinitie to <hi>Han<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>burgh, Doctor Philip. Nicolaj,</hi> now in the LORD, who appearantly hath beene graced, and indued with a gift of prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, as experience and event of time, hath teſtified in his travels, &amp; who is the right fundamentall ground of this worke and prophecie, written by him <hi>33.</hi> yeares ſince, namely in the yeare of CHRIST <hi>1596,</hi> which was found extant preſently after him in Latine, and thereafter tranſlated in the Germane tongue by <hi>M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Gothard Artus</hi> to <hi>Da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſick,</hi> namely in the yeare of CHRIST <hi>1598.</hi> whereout a <hi>Dence</hi> Profeſſor called <hi>Niels Michelſone</hi> hath
<pb facs="tcp:6606:3"/>
gathered this briefe worke, and tranſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againe in <hi>Dence</hi> and Printed lately Anno <hi>1628.</hi> The ſubſtance is a briefe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalogie of times conferred with Scripture, out of <hi>Ezekiell, Daniel,</hi> and <hi>Revelation</hi> of <hi>Iohn,</hi> containing a Prophecie and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe of the Ghospell to the worlds end, &amp; concluded with the Authors protestation, which I thought good to tranſlate, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companie with an exhortation to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and benefite mine owne Nation with the ſame. Heerewith perſuading my ſelfe of acceptance, I doe thruſt this poore myte of my travels into the treaſurie of your Chriſtian and charitable dispoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, recommending it vnto the protection and tuition of your Honourable wiſdomes, and you and your doings vnto the grace of GOD.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Yours in CHRIST IESVS David Forbes.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:6606:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>TO</hi> The Chriſtian READER.</head>
            <p>GEntle Reader I haue thought good to benefite thee with this little worke, <hi>de regno CHRISTI;</hi> and to tranſlate it in our owne commoun lang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uage, that it may come in publict view of all: which I haue out of loue and for thy ſpirituall well pervſed: accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied with a breefe treatiſe, and exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to repentance, requeſting thee, as a ſpirituall freind, to cover my weak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and imperfection therein with the vaile of charitable cenſure: but as for the tranſlation it ſelfe, I ſhall approue it before all cenſurs whatſomever: my Maſter may well pretend it not to be decored with the ornate phraſe of lang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uage, but yet I hope he muſt ſubſcryue it to be the true tranſlation, according to the <hi>German</hi> and <hi>Dence</hi> phraſe it ſelfe, which wee ought receaue in good part, ſeing the Hiſtories and Prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies
<pb facs="tcp:6606:4"/>
both of <hi>Ezekiel, Daniel,</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velation</hi> of <hi>Iohn</hi> haue (as it were) hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto beene dark; but now in the end dayly more and more opned and clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red ſo well by faithfull Preachers, as alſo by dayly experience, which the Prophets doe teſtifie clearely, that men ſhall bee enlightned in thoſe myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries at the end, as you can remark in the Authors warrand for ſearching of the Scriptures, wherein we ſee plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a ſpeciall illumination of the Spirit, prophecied vnto ſome, for opening of all hid prophecies, and partes of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: yet albeit it is no wayes the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors meaning abſolutely to determine and appoynt vnto GOD the tyme and end of theſe things, which ſecreete the Father hath reſerved for himſelfe only, as he proteſteth heere in the end, for the yeere, day, and houre wee may not know: but yet of all tokens which our LORD IESUS hath revealed vnto vs, as likewayes the experience of our tymes, conferred and compared with
<pb facs="tcp:6606:5"/>
theſe Prophecies, wee can eaſily diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerne, that all theſe prophecies are moſt fulfilled; and that the world will ſoone take an end, and therefore ſhould ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh vs to haue the lampes of our heartes prepared, that wee may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy our Brydgroome the LORD IESUS into that bleſſed Heaven of all happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: To whom with the Father, and the holy Ghoſt bee all praiſe and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, AMEN.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine in the LORD DAVID FORBES.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="biblical_justification">
            <pb facs="tcp:6606:5"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE AVTHORS WARRAND</hi> for ſearching of Scripture.</head>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>DANIEL. 12. verſe 4.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>BVT thou, O Daniel, ſhut vp the words and ſeale the booke till the end of the time: many ſhall runne to and fro, &amp; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge ſhall bee encreaſed.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Verſe 9.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>And hee ſaid, Goe thy way, Daniel: for the words are cloſed vp, and ſealed, till the end of the time.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Verſe 10.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Many ſhall be purified, made white &amp; tried: but the wicked ſhall do wickedly, &amp; none of the wicked ſhall haue vnderstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: but the wiſe ſhall vnderstand.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>IEREMIAH. 23. Verſe 20.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>In the latter dayes yee ſhall vnderſtand it plainely.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6606:6"/>REVELATION. 10. verſe 7.</bibl>
               <p>But in the dayes of the voyce of the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth Angel, when he ſhall beginne to blow the trumpet, even the mysterie of GOD ſhall bee finiſhed, as hee hath declared to his ſervants the Prophets.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Verſe 11.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>And hee ſaid vnto mee, Thou must propheſie againe amongſt the people and nations, and tongues, and to many Kings.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">IWP</seg>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:6606:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>CHRONOLOGIA <hi>SACRA,</hi> THE CALLING TYME OF <hi>THE IEWES.</hi> 41 ½ Yeares.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">Y</seg>Eare after the birth of CHRIST 29 <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> began to preach repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, and to baptize.</p>
            <p>And in the ſaid yeare be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan the time of the Iewes mercifull calling, which conteineth in it ſelfe 41 ½. yeares, Apoc. 14.15.</p>
            <p>Anno <hi>Christi</hi> 30. <hi>Chriſt</hi> was baptized, and then diſcovered himſelfe to the people whom he was, and that by his preaching and miracles.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 31 <hi>Iohn Baptiſt</hi> is caſt in priſon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno Christi</hi> 32 he was beheaded.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anno Christi</hi> 34 <hi>Christ</hi> was cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified,
<pb facs="tcp:6606:7"/>
ſtood vp, and aſcended into Heaven.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The calling tyme of the Gentils <hi>1600</hi> yeares.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ANno Chriſti</hi> 70 endeth the calling tyme of the <hi>Iewes,</hi> when their chiefe Citie, and whole policies were deſtroyed to the ground: and in their place goeth on the calling tyme of the <hi>Gentils,</hi> of the which <hi>Christ</hi> gathereth now his Church, which mercifull cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the <hi>Gentils</hi> indureth 1600 yeares, as it is written in the <hi>Revelation</hi> chap. 14. verſe 20, and is vnderſtood by the 1600 furlongs: adde vnto this 1600 this 70, ſo is the end of the <hi>Gentils</hi> calling finiſhed <hi>anno Christi</hi> 1670.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Gogs, Magogs, or the Turks King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome began anno Christi <hi>335,</hi> and indureth <hi>1335</hi> yeares.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ANno Chriſti</hi> 335, is that evill and damnable heretique <hi>Arrius,</hi> who for his hereticall learning was excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate by a generall aſſemblie; yet to <hi>Synodo</hi> and <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> was accepted,
<pb facs="tcp:6606:7"/>
and made free againe with his doctrine, which <hi>Arianiſh</hi> doctrine was the firſt beginning vnto the <hi>Gogs</hi> and <hi>Mahu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mets</hi> abſurdities, which were accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and believed in the ruined citie of <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> and eſpecially heerefra <hi>an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no Christi</hi> 335, began the <hi>Goges</hi> 1335 yeares, and endeth <hi>anno Christi</hi> 1670, <hi>Daniel</hi> 12. verſe 11.12: and heere is the beginning on that two tymes, and an halfe tyme, <hi>Daniel,</hi> 12. verſe 7.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 366, <hi>Damaſius</hi> and <hi>Vrſatius</hi> had great contention and diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie about the ſeate of the Pope, heerefra began the tyme of the two witneſſes clothed in Sackcloth, who ſhould pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecie 1260 dayes. <hi>Revel.</hi> 11 3.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>THE POPES BEGINNING.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ANno Christi</hi> 410 <hi>Rome</hi> is taken and burnt by <hi>Alaricus</hi> King of the <hi>Gothes,</hi> never was the Citie of <hi>Rome</hi> vanquiſhed any tyme before, neither gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven over vnto any ſtranger, and out lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſh, ſince the beginning of the fourth Monarchy, &amp; at that time <hi>Sozimus</hi> was
<pb facs="tcp:6606:8"/>
Pope, who ardently ſtood after the <hi>Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumenick</hi> ſtyle, that is, that hee might be called the common and head Biſhop a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue the whole clergie, everie where els through the whole world: This <hi>So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zimus</hi> gaue ſuch a law that no doings in the Kirke ſhould ſtand in full power without it was approved, and conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the Biſhop of <hi>Rome,</hi> after as it was prophecied that the ſonne of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition ſhould then begin his gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nament when the Romane Kingdome began to bow, for certainly that over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throw of the Romanes, which was done by <hi>Alaricus,</hi> hath beene a beginning hithertill: Therefore that the Papiſtes time which is 1260 yeares, or the 42 months, everie month reckoned to 30 dayes, and everie day for a yeare, hath heere his beginning of this 410 yeares of Chriſt, which 410 yeares added to 1260 the ſumme is 1670. when the Popedome with all things will only take an end.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 452. The <hi>Hunners</hi> King
<pb facs="tcp:6606:8"/>
                  <hi>Attila</hi> is come in <hi>Italie,</hi> who ſpoyled and deſtroyed many Cities, and townes, from this 452 yeares falleth in the <hi>Gogs</hi> ſecreete dayes whereof <hi>Ezek</hi> 38.14.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 520, <hi>Anaſtaſius</hi> Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour began to baniſh and roote out all heriticques, with all their hereticall do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, wherevnto the Romane Pope helped with all his vttermoſt power: &amp; which attained vnto a proſperous ſucceſſe; whereby Sathan the father of lyes, and all heriticall doctrine, was bound from this 520 yeares a thouſand yeares. In the which the Dragon that olde ſerpent, which is the Deuill and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, is ſaid to bee bound by the Angel with a great chayne, whereof <hi>Apoc.</hi> 20.2.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno Christi</hi> 597 <hi>is Gregorius Mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus</hi> made Pope, who would not let ſtyle him with the <hi>Oecumenick</hi> tytle o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Eaſt land, yet nevertheleſſe ſhewed his ambition &amp; avaritiouſneſſe, in this he ſubdued vnder him the Kirks of <hi>Spaine</hi> and <hi>Britaine,</hi> to his juriſdicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.
<pb facs="tcp:6606:9"/>
In this yeare <hi>Mahumet</hi> was 26 yeares old; and then doubtleſſe gaue him ſelfe to reaving and murther. Therefore beginneth the houre, day, moneth, and yeare, whereof <hi>Apoc.</hi> 9.15.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 636, Heereto indureth the time of the <hi>Gogs,</hi> Now after follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth his tyme <hi>Daniel</hi> 12.7. and then is <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> come vnder the <hi>Saracines</hi> power right in the 300 yeares after the clergie conſented vnto that moſt abſurd learning of <hi>Arrius.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno Christi</hi> 1450, beginneth the new Teſtaments joyfull yeares, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout that time is <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> with the whole Eaſt-landiſh Kingdome, and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perordome ſubdued by the Turkes and becommeth the <hi>Gogiers</hi> ſtall and ſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king denne. Heere beginneth the 7 an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall months, which the Scripture giveth vnto <hi>Gogs</hi> ſprituall burials <hi>Ezek-</hi> 39.11.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1522. Heereto endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the ſet tymes, now after followeth the halfe time <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.7.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6606:9"/>This ſame yeare Doctor <hi>Martin Luther</hi> went to <hi>Wormes,</hi> and anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red his cauſe before the Emperour. In the meane tyme <hi>Caroloſtadius</hi> made vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rore, and ſtormed to <hi>Wittenbergh,</hi> and the locuſts came vp, of the which <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocal.</hi> 9. verſe. 3.4.5.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno Christi</hi> 1625. heere endeth the 1290 yeares, whereof <hi>Daniel</hi> ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth in his 12 chap. verſe 11. and the 45 yeares beginneth heere.</p>
               <p>Right ſo endeth the ſame yeare the yeare of the two witneſſes, which when they are ended, then ſhall the Pope in-arme himſelfe with his greateſt power, and that ſhall bee his greateſt tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, which ſhall ſtand three yeares and an halfe, <hi>Apocal.</hi> 11.9. vntill <hi>anno Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti</hi> 1629, in the which yeare the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall tyme beginneth, which ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue 41 yeares and an halfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno Christi</hi> 1663, the 7 moneths haue their end.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1664, the laſt 7 yeares begin, of the which <hi>Ezek.</hi> 39.9.12.14.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6606:10"/>But <hi>anno Chriſti</hi> 1670, then haue all the yeares which the Prophets haue ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken of their only end, both the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, Gogs, and Popes, as afterwards the Author himſelfe cleareth, yet his proteſtation excepted, that he will not preceeſlie determine ſuch things; but referreth tyme, and houre into the Fathers owne hands.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>A ſhort interpretation, and clea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of the regiſter of the new Testament.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>THE whole age of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, according to the meaning of the Prophets, are divided in 4 times.</p>
                  <p>The firſt is the calling time of the <hi>Iewes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſecond is the <hi>Gentiles</hi> 1600 furlongs.</p>
                  <p>The third is <hi>Gogs, Mahumets,</hi> or <hi>Turkes</hi> tyme.</p>
                  <p>The fourth is, the Popes tyme.</p>
               </argument>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The firſt: Namely, the called time of the <hi>Iewes.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:6606:10"/>VVEE read in the booke of the <hi>Revelation</hi> 14. v. 15, is cryed and ſaid, THE TIME IS COME TO REAPE.</p>
                  <p>Now is a time or an houre, the foure and twentieth part of a whole day: night and day reckoned to 24 houres. An Heavenly day conteineth a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand yeares, as it is written 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. v. 8. (a thouſand yeares as a day) di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide this 1000 with 24, ſo commeth there about 41 yeeres and an halfe.</p>
                  <p>Remarke now the groundleſſe mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie of the Almightie GOD, how he did viſite and call his people the <hi>Iewes,</hi> of the ſeede of <hi>Abraham,</hi> and offered them his grace by <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptist,</hi> who began his calling with the preaching of repentance; and Baptiſme, in the 29 yeare or thereby, after the birth of <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Christ,</hi> of the Virgin <hi>Marie:</hi> which mercifull calling of the <hi>Iewes, Chriſt</hi> with his Diſciples continued after the beheading of <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> vnto one or two and fourtie yeares, and did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin
<pb facs="tcp:6606:11"/>
in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and gaue them time eneugh of repentance, in the ſpace of this 41 yeares, but when they remained in their hardneſſe, and condemned <hi>Gods</hi> Sonne, the bleſſed ſeede, which parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularlie, and eſpecially was promiſed them in <hi>Abraham,</hi> and ſo wittingly proceded in their ſinne, againſt the holy Ghoſt. Then GOD tooke his ſcourge in hand, <hi>Titus <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>espaſian,</hi> and therewith ſtrooke them ſo hard, in the end of this 41 yeares, or 41 and an halfe yeares af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the beginning of <hi>Iohns</hi> preaching, which was <hi>Anno Christi,</hi> 29. ſo that <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> their head Citie is deſtroyed, and their whole polices vndergone, and never ſhall come vp againe. Lay now together 29 with 41, ſo commeth thereof 70. Namely, in the ſame yeare after the birth of CHRIST, in the which yeare <hi>Titus</hi> deſtroyed <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and the policies of the Iewes, and this is the time of the Iewes calling <hi>Apocal.</hi> 14.15.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The other tyme of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: namely, the <hi>Gentils,</hi> which ſhould indure <hi>1600</hi> yeares.
<pb facs="tcp:6606:11"/>
SACRA,</head>
                  <p>AFter as the <hi>Iewes,</hi> GODS owne people, had contemned his Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly offerings of grace, in his Sonne IE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SUS CHRIST, and would not accept of grace, yet GOD would haue his glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Kingdome after this lyfe repleni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and therefore by his Word, Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments, and powerfull preſence of his Spirit, ordaineth heere in the world a Kingdome of grace for poore <hi>Gentils,</hi> that were not of <hi>Abrahams</hi> bleſſed ſeede as the <hi>Iewes,</hi> which Kingdome of grace ſhould reach it ſelfe out 1600 furlongs, as it is written <hi>Apocal.</hi> 14 19.20, with which furlongs are vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood yeares, as heereafter ſhall bee ſpoken of.</p>
                  <p>This 1600 furlongs, <hi>stadia,</hi> or yeares, which remaineth now againe for the Heathens to repent; and thereby to be in gathered in the Kingdome of grace, that they thereafter ſhould inherite his Kingdome of glory, and there ſee him as he is.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:6606:12"/>In this 1600 yeares the third An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell rypeth the vyneyard, as <hi>Iohn</hi> ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, and caſteth it in the great wine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe of GODS wrath: and the wine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe was troden without the citie, and blood came out of the winepreſſe vnto the horſe brydels, by the ſpace of 1600 furlongs. <hi>Revel.</hi> 14.19.20.</p>
                  <p>The three Angels with the Sonne of man that ſate on the white clowd, is, GOD Father, Sonne, and holy Ghoſt: <hi>Revel.</hi> 14.14. GODS Sonne is called the Sonne of man, for the humane na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture hee hath taken vnto the vnion and vnſeparabilitie of his perſon, the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Temple, verſe 15. the Heavenly Altar, verſe 18: the white clowd, v. 14. ſignifieth all one; namely, the ſame man IESUS CHRIST, <hi>In whom dwelleth the fulneſſe of the Godhead bodily.</hi> Coloſſ. 2.9.</p>
                  <p>The wyne grapes in the 18 verſe that are caſt in the preſſe of the wrath of GOD, are the <hi>Iewes,</hi> who were ſo preſſed by <hi>Titus <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>espaſian,</hi> that there
<pb facs="tcp:6606:12"/>
were ſlaine eleven hundreth thouſand <hi>Iewes,</hi> as <hi>Ioſephus</hi> writeth, lib. 7.</p>
                  <p>Theſe who were preſſed without the citie, <hi>verſe</hi> 20, and without the townes communitie, who were Burgeſſes and indwellers, <hi>Christ</hi> advertiſing them, they liſtned, and gaue eare to his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertiſement, who departed in ſafetie vnto <hi>Pella:</hi> in the meane tyme the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wyne grapes were preſſed by the armie of <hi>Titus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The blood that ranne from the preſſe betokneth, that the wrath of GODS vengeance ſhould reach without <hi>Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> and ſtreatch it ſelf vnto ſuch con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temners of GOD, and hardned ſinners, and that vnto 1600 furlongs, that is, 1600 yeares.</p>
                  <p>The horſe vnto whoſe brydles the blood ran, betokeneth the furious and vntamed Heathen, and tyrants, that ſet them-ſelves vp againſt CHRISTS Kirk. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2. Which tyrants are like Horſe &amp; Mules, in whom are no know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of ſalvation. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.9. who
<pb facs="tcp:6606:13"/>
ſhould bee caſt in the great preſſe of the wrath of GOD, vntill ſo long they let tame them by the brydle of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangel, and let them bee teached and ſhowne by the ſervants of the Word, to ſerue the LORD, and kiſſe the Sonne. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.10.11.12.</p>
                  <p>With 1600 <hi>Stadia,</hi> or furlongs is not vnderſtood, the length of place, but of tyme wherevnto is given three cauſes.</p>
                  <p>Firſt: CHRIST ſaith, (<hi>Luke.</hi> 21.24) That Ieruſalem ſhall bee troden vnder the feete of the Gentiles, vntill the time of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> bee fulfilled: Heere ſpeaketh IESUS of the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> that they ſhould haue a time, and that the <hi>Gentiles</hi> tyme ſhould beginne when <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſalem</hi> was deſtroyed, which time of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> is not found written in no place of the holy Scripture, how long it ſhall endure except only in this place. Secondly: This ſecret of 1600 <hi>ſtadia</hi> if it ſhould be vnderſtood according to the letter, and as the words are in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: then this 1600 <hi>stadia</hi> or fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs,
<pb facs="tcp:6606:13"/>
maketh no more than 50 myles: but now the cup of GODS wrath hath powred it ſelfe more at large than 50 myles about <hi>Ieruſalem:</hi> yea in all the corners of the whole earth: therefore this 1600 <hi>ſtadia,</hi> is not vnderſtood of the place, but of the tyme.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly: It is commonly the forme of the holy Ghoſt, that he opneth ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed tymes, <hi>(definita tempora)</hi> with ſome dark kynd of ſpeach. <hi>Daniel</hi> 4. he calleth the ſeven yeares, ſeven tymes. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 4. <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. hee giveth to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand yeares with dayes. <hi>Ezek.</hi> 47.3.4.5. there is meaſured 4000 cubits, vntill the Evangelicall fiſhing, where vndoubtedly is vnderſtood with 4000 cubits 4000 yeares: namely, from the firſt promiſe of the womans ſeede, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the Evangelicall fiſhing beganne with the fiſhers of IESUS CHRIST: The holy Apoſtles heereof can be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood in this place, with 1600 <hi>sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia,</hi> right ſo many yeares.</p>
                  <p>So indureth the <hi>Heathings</hi> appoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
<pb facs="tcp:6606:14"/>
tyme after this calculation vntill the Sonne of man come in his white clowd, who with his Angels will reape and gather the children of men, the good and fruitfull grapes in his owne citie, but will cutte off the wyld grapes with his ſharp ſickle till the 1670 yeares.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The third tyme of the New Testament: Namely, Gogs, Magogs, or Mahumets, and Turkes Kingdome: and that for the space <hi>1335.</hi> yeares, which is ended anno Chriſti <hi>1670.</hi> according to the prophecie of Daniel. <hi>12.</hi> v. <hi>12.</hi> and Dan. <hi>7.</hi> ver. <hi>8.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IN the foreſaid chapters of <hi>Daniel</hi> is written, that this little horne of <hi>Gogs</hi> or <hi>Mahumets,</hi> which came vp with a little beginning, and ſtoode vp amongſt the ten hornes, the ten King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes of the Romiſh Monarchs who did plucke away three of the firſt horns, and held warres againſt the Sanctuarie, and was for them too ſtrong, verſe. 11 This little horne came vp <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 335: when that <hi>Arianiſh</hi> hereſie ſpred foorth in denying of the Godhead of
<pb facs="tcp:6606:14"/>
IESVS CHRIST, in that publicke aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblie of Biſhops, and learned till <hi>Synodo,</hi> of all was conſented and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved, and that in the ruined Citie of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> which falſe doctrine of <hi>Arius</hi> was the firſt cauſe, and begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, till <hi>Gogs</hi> and <hi>Mahumets</hi> ſucceſſe in the world: ſo ſhall the end of this <hi>Gogs, Magogs,</hi> or <hi>Turkes,</hi> and <hi>Mahu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mets</hi> fall, after this calculation in the yeare 1670. for 1335 added vntill 335. makes in ſumme 1670.</p>
                  <p>Secondly: There is written in the <hi>Revelalion</hi> 9. <hi>verſe</hi> 14. of the foure Angels that were bound in the river <hi>Euphrates:</hi> that they ſhould bee made lowſe, which were prepared at one houre, at one day, at one moneth, and at one yeare to ſlaye the third part of men, which doubleſſe is vnder ſtood of the <hi>Mahumets</hi> tyrannie, which he exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted on the poore Chriſtians in the Eaſt Lands, and how he changed lawes, and times: for <hi>Euphrates</hi> flood is not farre from <hi>Babylon.</hi> The foure Angels
<pb facs="tcp:6606:15"/>
that are ſaid to bee bounde in this flood, or the foure Patriarchs in the Eaſt land, the one to <hi>Conſtantin,</hi> the other to <hi>Antiochia,</hi> the third to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> the fourth to <hi>Alexandria,</hi> which foure helped, and much aſſiſted the Kingdome of the ſonne of perdition. Theſe are ſaid to bee louſed, and many wayes ſpred abrode, and that by the hereſie of <hi>Arius</hi> and <hi>Neſtorius,</hi> concerning the abſurd doctrine of CHRISTS perſon, that when they had conſented in the ſame hereſie, then are they forced to giue themſelves vnder <hi>Mahumet,</hi> and then were prepared till the houre, day, moneth and yeare, to ſlay the third part of men. Let now one houre bee the 24 part of one heavenly day which continueth almoſt 42 yeares, for one whole day is reckoned for a thouſand yeares: the Heavenly moneth 30 yeares ſpace, this yeare being a common yeare: ſo extendeth the ſumme 1073. yeares.</p>
                  <p>Now when the end falleth in <hi>Anno Christi</hi> 1670 then is the beginning <hi>anno Christi</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:6606:15"/>
579, in the which tyme, as the <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> that were in <hi>Spaine</hi> turned from that <hi>Arianiſh,</hi> and <hi>Mahumetiſh</hi> do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, which then long tyme was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed and approved of the foure Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triarchs: and therewith tooke ſuch an end, that <hi>Mahumet</hi> troade himſelfe, who till in this 597 yeares was in the bloome of his youth, about 26 yeares of age: Moreover in this ſame yeare the Popes ambition ſhew it ſelfe, and avaritious flood <hi>Euphrates</hi> in the Pope <hi>Gregorius Magnus,</hi> who ſent his Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors in <hi>England,</hi> and by power of an armie forced them to imbrace the <hi>Romiſh</hi> religion: In like manner the Pope had the victorie aboue the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of <hi>Spaine.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly: <hi>Ezekiel</hi> chap. 39. verſe 11 doth prophecie, that GOD ſhall giue <hi>Gog</hi> a buriall place towards the Eaſt, which ſhall be called the valley of the multitude of <hi>Gog,</hi> where <hi>Gog</hi> with his armies ſhall be buried, and cleanſe the land in ſeven moneths, and ſhall burne
<pb facs="tcp:6606:16"/>
off their weapons, and put the ſhields and bucklers vpon bowes, and vpon arrowes with fire ſeven yeares, verſe 9. when there is made of the ſeven Angelicall moneths Angelicall dayes, 30 dayes in everie moneth, and dayes to the yeare, ſo commeth of it 210 yeares: adde vnto this ſeven yeares, in the which the weapons were burnt in, Summa 217 yeares: Let now the end of this 217 yeares fall in 1670, and then 217 ſubſtracted from this 1670, the beginning falleth <hi>anno</hi> 1453. In the which tyme <hi>Mahumet</hi> 11 of the name tooke in <hi>Constantinople,</hi> and made heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with an end of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Emperour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome in the Eaſt land: ſo is then <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantinople Gogs</hi> buriall place, and the valley of the multitude of the <hi>Gogs,</hi> or that place <hi>Hamona,</hi> verſe 16, that ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth toward the Eaſt vnto the ſea, verſe 11, which <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> is not longer the Chriſtians head citie in the Eaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, as before; but <hi>Gogs</hi> denne, and ſpirituall dead ſtinking graue of the
<pb facs="tcp:6606:16"/>
                     <hi>Mahumets.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That theſe armour arrowes ſhould burne ſeven yeares, ſignifieth that the <hi>Mahumetiſh</hi> lawes, ſtatutes, ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies, Kirkes ſervice, and deceate ſhould be burnt to nothing, by the fire of the true ſpirituall word of GOD.</p>
                  <p>This is now of <hi>Gogs, Mahumets,</hi> and <hi>Turks</hi> Kingdome, how long it will indure: namely, as long as the tyme of the New Teſtament indureth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="section">
                  <head>The fourth tyme of the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament: namely, the Popes.</head>
                  <p>IN the booke of the <hi>Revelation,</hi> 13 chap. there is written of the ſeven headed beaſt, that it ſhould continue 42 moneths, that is, the Popedome to <hi>Rome</hi> ſhall indure 42 moneths. <hi>Rome</hi> is builded on ſeven heads, high toppes, and mountaines: Make monethes to dayes 30 dayes in everie moneth, and reckon every day for a yeare, ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedeth 1260 yeares, when the end of this 1260 yeares falleth in <hi>anno Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſti</hi>
                     <pb facs="tcp:6606:17"/>
1670. and then beginneth the ſame 1260 yeares, <hi>anno Chriſti</hi> 410: from which tyme hitherto <hi>Rome</hi> hath had the empyre and victory almoſt over all the borders of the <hi>Iewes:</hi> then firſt ſubdued and taken in by <hi>Alaricus</hi> King of the <hi>Gothes,</hi> then began the firſt Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Monarchie to be feeble, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate weake legges.</p>
                  <p>Now when ſuch wayes the policies and mightie government of <hi>Rome</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan to diminiſh, then began the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſh Antichriſt to increaſe in the go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of the Church, and the Pope tooke vnto himſelfe the power, and ſuperioritie aboue the whole world, in all Churches, and clergie, even as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> had prophecied before 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 6 ſaying ſo. <hi>And now yee know what withholdeth that hee might bee revealed in his tyme:</hi> namely, that man of ſinne, and ſonne of perdition, ſetteth himſelfe againſt: <hi>verſe.</hi> 7. <hi>For the misterie of iniquitie doeth already worke, onely hee which now withholdeth
<pb facs="tcp:6606:17"/>
ſhall let, till he be taken out of the way:</hi> which <hi>Pauls</hi> prophecie, <hi>Chriſostomus,</hi> and many others vnderſtood this of the Romiſh Monarchy, &amp; Emperourdome, which then hindred the ſonne of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, and man of ſinne his ambition, that he could not come vp as he would: and which could not bee done, vntill the time, the ſame <hi>Imperium</hi> and Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perourdome began to bow, which was accompliſhed by <hi>Alaricus</hi> King of the <hi>Gothes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">II. In the <hi>Revelation</hi> 18, <hi>Iohn</hi> heareth of proud <hi>Babylon,</hi> whoſe plagues, death, and ſorrows ſhall one day fall vpon her. <hi>verſe</hi> 8, and in an houre ſhall her judgment bee, <hi>verſe</hi> 10, And in an houre ſhall the deſolation of her riches come. <hi>verſe</hi> 17. And in an houre ſhall bee made deſolate. <hi>verſe</hi> 19. So will GOD then powre his wrath on the ſeed of the Romanes in one day, &amp; 3 houres. Now one day is 1000 yeares, one hour 41 and an halfe yeares, adde together, ſo is the ſumme 1124. and an halfe yeares,
<pb facs="tcp:6606:18"/>
when this 1124. and a half yeares endeth <hi>An. Christi</hi> 1670. then falleth their be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning in <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 546. in the which time, that the <hi>Gothers</hi> King <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilias,</hi> that ſaid himſelfe to be the ſcourge of GOD, ſet fire in <hi>Rome,</hi> and brunt the greateſt part thereof. From this 546 yeare of Chriſt, vntill <hi>Luther</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted in the Lord, is likewiſe 1000 yeares one Heavenly day, for he died <hi>Anno Christi</hi> 1546. and is that day of the which before: therefrom and till 1588, when as the Papiſts contracted themſelves againſt <hi>England,</hi> and there gote a terrible defeate, went out the firſt houre of the three, therefrom and till <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1629. When as the Papiſts tyrannie ſhall bee weakned, and muſt vnder-goe, and the two wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes ſhall come on feete againe, is the other houre from 1629. vntill 1670. is the third houre, when all things will ſeeme to take their only end.</p>
                  <p n="3">III. In the <hi>Revelation</hi> 9. The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſeeth, a ſtarre which had the key
<pb facs="tcp:6606:18"/>
of the bottomleſſe pit, and was fallen downe from Heaven on the earth, wherewith nothing is vnderſtood, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept only this ſonne of perdition, who opned the bottomleſſe pit. <hi>v.</hi> 2. where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out there aroſe much hereticall ſmoake damp and reeke, which darkned the righteous beames of the Sunne of IE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SUS CHRIST, and his Evangelicall doctrine, and out of that ſmoke came Locuſtes on the earth, <hi>v.</hi> 3. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with is vnderſtood the peſtilentious heretickes and falſe teachers, who doe nothing els but bring in amongſt the ground &amp; ſeede of the Chriſtian Kirk the greateſt miſchiefe. Theſe damnable locuſts (faith <hi>Iohn</hi>) ſhall vexe the people 5 moneths, that is, 150 Heavenly dayes or yeares: for fiue tymes thirtie is 150, when this 150 yeares taketh their end, <hi>anno Christi</hi> 1670. then the calculation concludeth that they begin <hi>anno</hi> 1521. In the which tyme that <hi>Caroloſtadius</hi> wakned vp that great vprore, with ſtor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of images, from whence proceeded
<pb facs="tcp:6606:19"/>
in the Churches diverſities of opinions.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly: In the <hi>Revelation,</hi> chap. 11. we reade of the two witneſſes, clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed in ſackcloth, who prophecied 1260 dayes: and when 1260 dayes endeth, then they ſhall bee killed by the beaſt, and three dayes and an halfe ly vnbu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, but thereafter ſhall haue lyfe of the Spirit, and aſcend to the clowdes of Heaven, and the enemies of the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangell ſhall behold it; then ſhall there be a great Earthquake, which ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue an houre, in the which Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quake the tenth part of <hi>Babylon</hi> ſhall fall. By the two witneſſes is vnderſtood the old and new Teſtament, which bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth witneſſe of the trueth in murning weede and ſackcloth, that is, vnder cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and perſecution: If wee will adde and lay together with this three and an halfe dayes, or three and an halfe commoun yeares, the heavenly houre namely 41 an and half yeares, then is the ſumme 1305, then followeth it the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of this 1305, to bee <hi>Anno
<pb facs="tcp:6606:19"/>
Chriſti</hi> 365 on the which tyme that <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſius</hi> &amp; <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſicinus</hi> did contend to <hi>Rome</hi> for the Popedome, which of them ſhould bee Pope, who carried a bloody warre in the holy houſe againſt others. And then hath this ſonne of perdition gotten his kingdome, conſecrated and anoynted vnto him by murther, and ſhedding of much blood. When wee begin from the foreſaid yeare <hi>Anno Christi</hi> 365, to reckon to the 1260, then end they juſt <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1625. Now how thoſe two witneſſe the Old and New Teſtament with all true prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, who hath holden with thoſe two witneſſes, hath beene killed and rent, it is eneugh knowne vnto all men, for not onlie Papiſts, but all other ſects rent ſo on thoſe two witneſſe, and ſo killeth them, everie one to turne and revert them vnto his owne hereticall meaning, which is eneugh knowne vnto everie true Chriſtian, but now moſt of all thoſe two witneſſes are now killed with their confederats in this 3 and an halfe
<pb facs="tcp:6606:20"/>
yeares: Namely, from Anno 1625 vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till Anno Chriſti. 1629. whereof the well learned man Maſter <hi>Meynelaus Poulſone</hi> Preacher to the Caſtell of <hi>Copemanhaven,</hi> hath ſet out on our <hi>Dens</hi> tongue the foreſaid <hi>Philippi Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colai</hi> his words which likewiſe I will rehearſe following in this manner.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Comment. de regno CHRISTI, lib. <hi>2.</hi> capit. <hi>2.</hi> fol. <hi>6. 196.</hi> ſequent.</head>
               <p>SEing now the holy BIBLE is tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlated in <hi>Engliſh, French, Dutch, Dence;</hi> and other tongues and langua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges: and is vſed and reade with all di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligence, both of learned and vnlearned: So vnderſtandeth the Pope, that <hi>Scotiſh Engliſh, Fleames, Dence, Norwiſh, Swe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, Poles, Bohemiſh,</hi> and <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ngariſh;</hi> with no deceate or ſubtilitie can bee brought againe vnder his power, ſo long as the bookes of the old and new Teſtament haue the vpper hand: and therefore he ſhall ſtriue after alſo to take from theſe two witneſſes all their prerogatiue, and bring ſo to paſſe, that
<pb facs="tcp:6606:20"/>
they may haue no place in the Roman Church; but to loſſe their ſhine alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and by the permiſſion of GOD, ſeing Godlineſſe is verie rare beſides vs, ſo can it lightly event, that the Romiſh Antichriſt ſhall haue once ſucceſſe.</p>
               <p>This proud and diveliſh victorie will continue three yeares and an half, which is from the yeere 1625. vntill 1629, ſo long ſhall the Chriſtian Kirk indure this perſecution, and ſhed her blood in great quantitie, for confeſſing of the trueth: and together in theſe tymes men ſhall ſee the bookes of the old and new Teſtament to be whole con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temned, and to ly as dead bodies in the ſtreetes, and they ſhall bee troade with feete, yet ſome godly compaſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, and the Evangeliſh true confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors ſhall not ſuffer them to be whole buried. But thereafter from <hi>anno</hi> 1629 vntill <hi>anno</hi> 1670, the whole heavenly houre, or fourtie one yeares and a halfe, ſo ſhall kyth it ſelfe, that the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb facs="tcp:6606:21"/>
Scripture, and holy miniſter calling, with the two witneſſes, which is the old and new Teſtament, ſhall power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully come before againe, and with great <hi>jubileren,</hi> and eſpeciall joyfull crying, compaſſe about the godly, and aſcend vp into the clowdes of Heaven. <hi>Apoc.</hi> 11. <hi>ver.</hi> 12. this ſhall bee a great ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and glory, and can not bee hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered. This the Papiſts ſhall ſee, and over all meaſure therethrough bee ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified, ſeing they can not troade more the holy Bible vnder their feete; nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther turne the people with their <hi>ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>themata,</hi> or curſe and cruell perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, from the diligent reading, and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly meditation: yea, there ſhall be ſuch a great Earthquake, ſo that the tenth part of the great citie, <hi>Apocal.</hi> 11. <hi>ver.</hi> 13 that is, the ten Kingdomes of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſticall dominions ſhall condiſcend to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether: namely, the <hi>Germanians, Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garians, Bohemians, Polonians, Swedens, Dence, Norwiſh, Engliſh, Scottiſh,</hi> and <hi>French,</hi> who ſhall be moved, and ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:6606:21"/>
knit themſelues together, and wholly denunce themſelues off from the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts: yea, they ſhall hold together with ſuch a ſpeciall zeale, and that for the cruell perſecution of the Chriſtians, as likewiſe for the cauſe of the vntole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable pride of the Romane Antichriſt: And ſhall fall in <hi>Italie</hi> or Welſhland with mightie power, and burne vp with fire that great Citie <hi>Rome,</hi> great <hi>Babylon, Revel.</hi> 18. <hi>verſe</hi> 8. That <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylons</hi> whoore can bee payed, and get her right rewarde, who tyrannouſlie hath perſecuted the ſpirituall members of <hi>Chriſts</hi> bodie, <hi>Revel.</hi> 17. verſe. 6. and drunke her ſelfe drunke with the blood of Saincts, and blood of the Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyres of IESVS. And that there can come ſuch a reward vpon her, as on <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> who ſlew CHRIST IESUS himſelfe, and is come ſince the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning on all perſecuters of CHRISTS Church.</p>
               <p>After this tyme is the heavenly houre 41 and an halfe yeares, whoſe end
<pb facs="tcp:6606:22"/>
are fulfilled <hi>anno Chriſti</hi> 1670.</p>
               <p>Heerewith it aggreeth with that which our foreſaid author ſetteth in his expoſition, of the 12. chapter of <hi>Daniel, lib.</hi> 2. <hi>de regno Christi. pag.</hi> 121. ſaying, It may bee that <hi>Anno Christi</hi> 1625. will come vp ſome new <hi>Motus,</hi> and tumult, that the Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Church will ſuffer cruell ſorrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full tempeſts againe, but how it ſhall bee <hi>Daniel</hi> cleareth not, except that which hee heareth of the Angel, bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed are they that waiteth thereafter: that is, who are patient as yet, vntill the 45 yeare are paſt.</p>
               <p>Now everie one knoweth that pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience is no wayes without croſſes and ſorrowes, whereby may bee judged that Anno 1625, there will burſt out a hole on a diveliſh and peſtilentious byle, which now <hi>Anno Christi</hi> 1596, when <hi>Philip Nicolai</hi> wrote this booke, the enemies of the true Chriſtians, are making rype, in their ſecret counſels and concealed pratickes, that the Elect
<pb facs="tcp:6606:22"/>
may be weary of thoſe troublous times.</p>
               <p>Wherefore of this <hi>ineluctabilis</hi> and future tyme of ſorrows ſhall come on that tyme: vntill the which wee haue as yet from this yeare 1579 28 yeare, then ſhould the ſoules of true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians, after the counſell of <hi>Daniel,</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare theſelues to patience: and heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with remember this cruell perſecution, ſhall not for ever indure, but ſhall vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergoe, within a ſhort ſpace, and come to an end within few yeares, And therefore eſpecially ſhould wee pray GOD, that hee from Heaven will ſend vs the ſtrength of his ſpirit, that wee could grow in true faith, and ſtand con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in the revelation of the trueth.</p>
               <p n="5">V. And moreover this vndoubtedly agrieth well, namely, this laſt tyme of the new Teſtament, with the tymes that proceeded before the flood came, ſeing that CHRIST prophecieth here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of himſelfe. <hi>Math.</hi> 24. &amp; <hi>Luk</hi> 17. That right as it was in the world before the flood, the people gaue themſelues
<pb facs="tcp:6606:23"/>
to drunkenneſſe, filthineſſe and luſtes of the fleſh, and that vntill the ſame day that <hi>Noah</hi> entred into the Arke: So likewiſe the people ſhould giue themſelues ſecure vnto ſuch vices a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the laſt tymes.</p>
               <p>Seing there is now reckoned from the worlds beginning vnto the flood 1657 yeares: ſubſtract 1657 from 1670 ſo haſt thou againe 13 yeares, when CHRIST was 12 yeares, and in his 13 when hee diſputed with the learned in the Temple of <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Lay now together the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> with the ſecond, and then the earthly with the Heavenly.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The firſt had earthly Paradice, the other the Temple of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> and that after the commandement of his Heavenly Father: <hi>Shall I not be about my Fathers buſineſſe, Luke</hi> 2. <hi>ver.</hi> 49.</p>
               <p n="2">2. As <hi>Adam</hi> ſhew obedience vnto GOD in Paradice, ſo did the other in the Temple.</p>
               <p n="3">3. <hi>Adam</hi> was counſelled of the wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man,
<pb facs="tcp:6606:23"/>
that hee ſhould eate of the tree of the forbidden fruite: CHRIST could not be counſelled of his mother to deſiſt from that which was his Fathers.</p>
               <p n="4">4. As from <hi>Adams</hi> fall vntill the flood proceeded 1657 yeares, likewayes from <hi>Chriſts</hi> actiue obedience <hi>(obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>entiae activae specimine)</hi> example which he ſhew in the Temple, when he was 12 yeares full, and in his 13, vntil the only end and revelation of tyme will proceede 1657 yeares: adde heerevnto the 13 yeares of his age, ſo falleth in the end <hi>anno Chriſti</hi> 1670.</p>
               <p n="5">V. And for the laſt, it is neither to diſ-allow betweene the agreement of the yeares of <hi>Chriſts</hi> age, that he lived &amp; converſed viſibly in this world with ſo many of the New Teſtaments jubile, every commoun jubile yeare reckoned to 49, <hi>Levit.</hi> 25. <hi>ver.</hi> 8. for 7 tymes 7, maketh 49. the next following 50 yeare was both a jubile yeare, and the firſt yeare to begin in: in the next following jubile yeares reckning. Now
<pb facs="tcp:6606:24"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6606:24"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb facs="tcp:6606:25"/>
is <hi>Christ</hi> dead, riſen, and aſcended in the 34 yeares of his age: begin now to tell theſe jubile yeares, from the 29 yeare of CHRISTS age, for then began <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> to ſounde with the trumpet of the new Teſtament, ſo falleth in this 34. this new Teſtaments jubile yeares, beginning <hi>Anno Chriſti</hi> 1646 from this, to 1670, is about 25 yeare, an halfe jubile yeare, becauſe CHRIST liued not out his 34 yeares.</p>
               <p>Now to a concluſion of this lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle booke, I will bring in two prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of our Authors.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="prophecy">
               <head>I. Of the diminiſhing of CHRISTS Church against the worlds end. Pag. <hi>223.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THIS may well bee, that as <hi>Chriſt</hi> did not ſhow himſelfe after his reſurrection to the vnthankfull Iewes preiſts, and Scribes in Ieruſalem, but remoued North vnto <hi>Galile,</hi> and there revealed himſelfe before his diſciples: ſo in like manner, that the cleare lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb facs="tcp:6606:25"/>
of the Evangel, which once is driven from ſome parts in Dutchland, and Romiſh dominions, ſhall not come their againe: in the ſame places, but make his dwelling away, North in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manie,</hi> and in other Northlandiſh pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, in <hi>Scotland, Norway, Sweden, Iſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And as CHRIST after his reſurre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction preached not, and learned pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lictly in <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> where he was cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cified, but ſecreetly revealed himſelfe to his diſciples, who were gathered within locked doores for feare of the <hi>Iewes:</hi> ſo that in like manner before the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aſt day, the Heavenly ſinceere doctrine <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n Churchs and ſchooles from whence ſhe is baniſhed, not more there to haue ſuch ſucceſſe, but ſhall ſound quietly within ſome poore folkes doores, who ſhall reade the holy BIBLE in their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ouſes, with <hi>Luthers Catechiſme</hi> and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſtles, and other writings of true <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>earned teachers, and with their houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>old profite themſelues in the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe
<pb facs="tcp:6606:26"/>
of true religion.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="prophecy">
               <head>What ſucceſſe <hi>Spaine</hi> hath to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spect heere in the <hi>Sownd.</hi> pag. <hi>99.</hi> lib. <hi>1.</hi> circa finem. cap. <hi>2.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IF <hi>Spaine</hi> out of ambition, for aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menting of his kingdome come in our ſeas, and will ſtay or hinder the handling and merchandiſe of the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh, Dence, Swedens</hi> and <hi>Muſcovi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters,</hi> vnto the damnage of the Norwiſh dominions, then it ſhall not proſper with him, he may try much, but carrie nothing home, but ſhame and diſcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moditie with him.</p>
               <p>This is now briefly ſet foorth and extracted by the honourable and inlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Doctor <hi>Philip Nicolaus,</hi> which is taken out of his ſecond booke of the Kingdome of IESUS CHRIST, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning a prophecie of the worlds end.</p>
               <p>If any heereby will conclude, that the laſt day preciſly ſhould fall in this 1670, and thinke heereby that I ſhould preſume more than the holy Scripture
<pb facs="tcp:6606:26"/>
giveth place. Therevnto I anſwere (ſaith the Author) in this manner, <hi>Of that day and houre no man knoweth; yea, not the Angels in Heaven,</hi> ſaith CHRIST, <hi>Math.</hi> 24.42. <hi>Mark.</hi> 13.32. For this cauſe I proteſt heere, and doe witneſſe, that I <hi>Philip Nicolaus</hi> will know nothing of the myſteriall things, which GOD hath preſerved on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for himſelfe in ſecreete, and will haue no man to know it, neither de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree this nor deny this: it may well bee that the laſt day giue himſelfe to know in the ſame 1670 yeares, it may likewayes bee thereafter, as the people leaſt thinke of, and living in their fleſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly luſtes and appetites, that the ſame day ſtealeth ſuddenly over them, it may well bee that the laſt day com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth ſooner for the cauſe of the elect, who fervently and heartfully think long thereafter, that they could once at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine an happie end of all ſinne, and of all their ſorrow, which both the world, and the Divell afflicteth them
<pb facs="tcp:6606:27"/>
with: for that which GOD hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved in ſecreete for himſelfe, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commeth vs not to ſearch therein: and therefore I abyde alone by the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vealed word, and the holy propheti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call and Apoſtolicall writings, what the events are on the laſt day is found written after GODS owne commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Revel.</hi> 11. ver. 11. and ver. 19. and chap. 10. ver. 11. which I in the feare of GOD red with great diligence, and deepe meditation, heerewith pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Almightie GOD, who hath ſpoken by his holy Prophets, and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles mouth, that hee for his godly goodneſſe, mercifully will aſſiſt ſome of his true Chriſtians, to reveile and cleare the ſecret myſterie of tymes, that are written in <hi>Ezekiel, Daniel</hi> and <hi>Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation.</hi> Therefore when I ſee narrow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie vnto the Heavenly Evangelicall harveſt, the Heavenly houre, and hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly <hi>Stadia,</hi> or furlongs: then I can not otherwayes as preciſlie conſider &amp; meditate of the revealed times, if
<pb facs="tcp:6606:27"/>
wee will reckone over the involued things which are infolded in the holy BYBLE: yet nowayes concluded heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, what ſhall follow heereafter. Where fore this that I write heere, I ſet them not as Articles of beleefe, but onely as the thing that a Chriſtian ſhould deſire and ſeeke after, recommen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding this vnto the event of tyme: ſeing there is no ſurer interpretation, and clearing of Prophecies as when they are fulfilled.</p>
               <p>O everlaſting good GOD, the ſpring of all wiſedome and grace, inlighten our ſpirits and darke vnderſtanding, with the light and clearneſſe of thy godly wiſdome, with the ſpring and fire of fervent charitie, that in vs all worldly vanities, luſtes of the fleſh and ſpring of pryde, may bee extingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed and quenched by the holy lampe of thy light, and that wee may rejoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce in our onelie and moſt excellent Iewell that thou hath given vs, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, our onely Saviour and Redeemer
<pb facs="tcp:6606:28"/>
and bee true obeyers all the dayes of our lyfe, yea in the midſt of death: to whom with thee, and the holy Ghoſt be praiſe and Glorie for ever Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <l>Qui paenitentiae dulcedinem libat,</l>
                  <l>Sacrificium pro peccatis libat.</l>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
         </div>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:6606:28"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A</hi> BRIEFE TREATISE <hi>AND EXHORTATION</hi> TO REPENTANCE.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>MATH. Chap. 3. verſe. 2.</bibl>
                  <p>Repent, for the Kingdome of Heaven is at hand.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>IN this booke we may ſee the long patience and ſuffering of GOD, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards his owne people the <hi>Iewes,</hi> who in the laſt tymes of their viſita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, did ſend his owne Sonne, the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour of mankynd, and that of the ſeede of <hi>Abraham,</hi> to ſtretch foorth his hands and armes, to ſaue and imbrace the rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of the loſt ſheepe of the houſe of <hi>I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſrael:</hi> but when they did contemne Gods Fatherly viſitation, and were offended with CHRIST IESUS, &amp; had crucified the King of Glorie, as lykewayes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after did perſecute in the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner all his diſciples, Apoſtles, and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants
<pb facs="tcp:6606:29"/>
of GOD: then GOD left them, and gaue them over vnto themſelues, and did begin his mercifull calling with the <hi>Gentiles,</hi> who were ſtrangers and aliants from the houſe of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> By whoſe viſitation likewiſe, wee may learne of the mercie and juſtice of <hi>God:</hi> for thoſe <hi>Gentiles</hi> of <hi>Aſia,</hi> and Eaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landiſh Dominions, haue had their owne tymes of GODS mercifull viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, but after many ſinnes commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, together with the perſecution of ſaincts, and contempt of the word, GOD hath removed his Candleſtickes from them, and hath given them over vnto vanities, and lyes, and is gone from them, and now in this laſt houre and tyme of the world, it hath plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him to erect his Church, and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleſticke within this Nation: And there fore, O happie, and thryſe happie are wee, if wee will acknowledge the tymes of our mercifull viſitation, and day of our calling, for the LORD of
<pb facs="tcp:6606:29"/>
glorie is ſtanding at the doore of our ſoules: and within this Nation wee haue had our owne tymes, where GOD hath knocked long with the hammers of his Word: and appearantly ſeing the word is contemned, and beareth no fruite in mens conſciences and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations, that GOD is departing from vs vnto another people, and yet ſtreat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching foorth his armes, and calling vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him all true Chriſtians, who will turne vnto him and repent them of their ſinnes, for certainly there is no ſinne which hath abounded in thoſe forraine Churches, but thoſe and more doth abound beſides vs, and giue the Church and Sainctes of GOD within this Nation bee not perſecuted with publict Tyrants, yet let the wiſe Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian ſee how ſhee is perſecuted, rent, and divided within her ſelfe, which doeth prognoſticate a fearefull depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of our kynd GOD, and a terrible judgement to hang over our heads, and would to God I ſay that our judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb facs="tcp:6606:30"/>
bee not worſe of all, if we take not heede in tyme: Therefore let vs bee wiſe, and learne of the figge tree, and of theſe tokens, to prepare our ſelues for our Bridegroome the LORD IESUS ſecond comming in the clowdes.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptist</hi> a forerunner of the Meſſias, the firſt trumpet of the Gho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell, is heere crying out, according to the Prophecie of <hi>Iſaiah, Prepare the wayes of the LORD, make his pathes ſtreight, againſt the first comming of the Meſſias. Amend your liues for the Kingdome of grace is at hand,</hi> and is to bee offered in the LORD IESUS to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verie true penitent, and belieuer of the Ghoſpell. Now in thoſe dayes our onely high Prieſt and Prophet, is cry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing vnto vs, and learning vs by the Parable of the figge tree in the Gho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell, <hi>that the Kingdome of glorie is at hand. Mat.</hi> 24.32. And that wee ſhould lift vp our heads, <hi>working our ſalvation in feare and trembling,</hi> wait<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting for the day of the LORD, for he
<pb facs="tcp:6606:30"/>
beeing the firſt trumpet of the Gho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell in thoſe dayes, his onely matter and aime was, in reſpect of the great defection, and diverſitie of religion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the <hi>Iewes:</hi> as likewiſe their true worſhip of God, was turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Phariſaicall and ſelfe loue of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; therefore hee was buſie pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paring the firſt way and comming of the LORD, and importing vnto them a Kingdome of grace to bee at hand, and therefore did exhort them vnto repentance, that they might enter and goe in into that Church militant heere on earth by this Kingdome of grace, now to bee offered, and reveiled vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them in the Meſſias, that thereafter they might bee found worthie againſt the ſecond comming of the Lord, to enter into the Church triumphant, and Kingdome of glorie..</p>
            <p>Our <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptiſts,</hi> and preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers in our tymes, haue greater occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, yea all preaching ſtooles whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever, being now the laſt trumpets of
<pb facs="tcp:6606:31"/>
the Ghoſpell, haue matter enough to cry out in thoſe words: <hi>Repent for the Kingdome of Heaven is at hand:</hi> even that Kingdome of glorie, where the Meſſias is not in his firſt comming, in the lykeneſſe of a ſervant, and in the baſeneſſe of his fleſh, to offer more the Kingdome of grace and mercie, in errecting a Church militant heere on earth, as in the dayes of <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſt:</hi> But now certainly comming in his ſecond comming in the clouds, convoyed of all the Angels, and trowpes of HEAVEN, as a powerfull judge, in full majeſticall glorie, to rander e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verie man according to his workes, where grace and mercie ſhall ceaſe to bee more offered, and where all hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie Saincts and bleſſed Elect, who were partakers of that Kingdome of grace, in the Church militant heere on earth, ſhall bee gathred in that triumphant, and glorious Church in the Heavens for ever. O bleſſed and thryſe bleſſed is that ſoule, who findeth and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth
<pb facs="tcp:6606:31"/>
himſelfe by the touchſtone of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, to bee a member in this Kingdome of grace, and Church mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litant heere on earth: hee ſhall be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred and linked ſo faſt vnto this bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed happineſſe and endleſſe joy of all Saincts: alſo that no creature in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven nor in earth, no, the gates of hell can ſeparate him from it. Therefore how diligent ſhould wee bee to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace this Kingdome of grace, in theſe latter tymes: ſeing the world is ſunck<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en into meere ſinne and vanitie, and all abhominations haue taken vpper hand, yea all ſignes and tokens prophecied in Scriptures are fulfilled, ſo that there reſteth nothing, except onely the ſigne of the Sonne of man comming in the clouds to judge the world, and take acompt of our actions, and which wee may as ſure expect daylie to come, as wee are certaine of things paſt: For Heaven and earth will periſh, but one jote or one word of the LORD ſhall not periſh. This ſpirituall echo re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembleth
<pb facs="tcp:6606:32"/>
well in our eares, as <hi>Iohn</hi> the <hi>Baptist</hi> would ſay, I exhort you to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, becauſe of thoſe miſerable times, in that godlineſſe amongſt you is thinne, and Phariſaicall deciſions, and other diverſities is in your Church, as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe all ſinne, and wickedneſſe aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth amongſt you, and the Kingdome of grace is at hand, now to bee offer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the Meſſias, and Sonne of GOD CHRIST IESUS, and which Kingdome of grace, who ſo receaveth by faith and repentance, now in this laſt time of your calling, ſhall inherit the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heaven, and Kingdome of glorie, and which Kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, no man can attaine vnto, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this true repentance, and amende<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of life, and which notable trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pet of repentance, may verie well bee applyed vnto this age: Therefore thou who readeſt this, and thou who bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt this, repent, amend thy life, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of thoſe evill and latter dayes, in that true godlineſſe is thinne amongſt
<pb facs="tcp:6606:32"/>
vs, and true religion, is rent and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered with all ſort of ſchiſmes, and diverſities in the Church of GOD, and the whole earth is overladen with wickedneſſe, and ſenceleſſe ſecuritie: Let vs now lift vp our heads, and light vp the lamps of our hearts, for the Kingdome of Heaven is at hand, where once grace ſhall reſt to bee offered, at which tyme all true penitents ſhall bee gathered, and inherite that bleſſed glorious, and everlaſting Kingdome of Heaven. The ſpirituall meaning of this text, importeth a circumſtance and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie of this repentance, as if hee would ſay, for the Kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven is at hand: and therefore it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſare that yee repent, and amend, for who ſo deſireth to bee partakers of this Kingdome of Heaven, hee can not come without this repentance: Alſo that this repentance is ſuch a neceſſare thing, that thou canſt not attaine vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſalvation without it; yea, thou canſt not bee more ſaued in the day of the
<pb facs="tcp:6606:33"/>
LORD without repentance, then <hi>Noah</hi> was ſaved without the Arke from the Flood. O happie is hee and thryſe happie, who attaineth vnto this ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied repentance, it is the pricke of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, it is the verie ſacrifice and faith of <hi>Abraham:</hi> it is the ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficing knyfe to mortifie the outward man. It is the firie and fervent burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing zeale of the ſoule, accompanied and endued with the ſpirit of prayer, and godly ſorrow, quenched with the teares of true repentance, and with a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable joy, and feeling of the mercies of GOD, yea, it bringeth vs vnto the verie ſacrifice it ſelfe, vnto the which <hi>Iſaack</hi> was a type: namely, vnto true faith in the Blood of IESVS. It is the budding rodde of <hi>Aaron,</hi> which ſhall bring foorth ſuch bloſſomes of a godly lyfe, and joy in the holy ſpirit heere in this earthly tabernacle, and in the morning in the Tabernacle of the teſtimonie: that is, when the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vening of thy time is paſt, and thou
<pb facs="tcp:6606:33"/>
art brought vnto the morning of thy endleſſe reſt, either by death, or the day of the LORD: then ſhall it budde and bloſſome vnto thee ſuch fruites of endleſſe and vnſpeakable happineſſe, as no tongue can bee able to expreſſe, nor heart to thinke of.</p>
            <p>It is the ſtrong hand of <hi>Iacob,</hi> who by faith will wreſtle, and take ſuch holde on CHRIST, that it will never leaue him, vntill the time hee be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed. Therefore good Chriſtian let vs conſider, what excellent times, and occaſion, wee haue as yet to day to repent, while that the gates of grace are open, let vs runne to this throne of grace, ſo long as it is offered in the Ghoſpell, and not delay the time of our repentance.</p>
            <p>Now is the Kingdome of Heaven at hand, even that glorious Kingdome of IESVS, when the gates of grace ſhall bee ſhut, and never offered no more, when no repentance, teares or prayers will prevaile.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:6606:34"/>Now I ſay, in this laſt evening and houre of the world, ſo long as CHRIST is ſtanding knocking with the hammer of his Ghoſpell at the doore of thy ſoule, refuſe not to open, leaſt the time of his ſtanding be now out, and thou then bee left and locked without the doores of his mercie, as a wretchfull and woefull reprobate for ever: then vnhappie man that euer thou was borne, thou ſhall then repent, but too late, and all thy repentance is then but ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gravating of thy ſorrowes, and never dying torments in hell for ever.</p>
            <p>The rich Glutton and reprobate, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ready there, would giue the whole earth if they did poſſeſſe it, to haue the time, place, and meanes of grace offered vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, as now wee haue: but they can not redeeme this time with thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands of worlds, &amp; mountaines of gold; not ſo much therefore be eaſed as for a minute of an houre out of their never dying torments.</p>
            <p>Therefore I would requeſt the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable
<pb facs="tcp:6606:34"/>
man, who in ſome ſence hath gotten a ſight and taſt of the mercies of GOD, and of thy effectuall calling in IESUS CHRIST, to conſider, meditate, and ponder with thy ſelfe of the feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full event, and end of the world now at hand: and therefore to preaſſe with all diligence to frame thy lyfe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation according to the preſcript word of GOD, and let our myndes be ſo occupied about heavenly things day<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and hourely, attending the comming of our LORD IESUS CHRIST, who aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuredly finding the lampe of thine heart prepared, with the oyle of grace, and teares of ſanctified repentance, will at that day transforme, and metamorphoſe thine earthie tabernacle into an immor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall body, where both ſoule and body ſhall enjoy that joy of all joyes, which is to behold the moſt comfortable ſight of GOD himſelfe: yea, that bleſſed con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>templation of the holy Trinitie, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with thy glorified ſoule ſhall bee fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led ſo with ſuch an vnexpreſſible and
<pb facs="tcp:6606:35"/>
vnſpeakable bleſſed joy comming from this maine Ocean, and fountaine of all happineſſe, that it ſhall overflow with joy, that it can not bee able to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teane more joy of it ſelfe, than the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence alone, and contemplation of GOD, which hee himſelfe ſhall fill it with: yea, ever enjoying and rejoycing, and never wearying; but ever praiſing and gloriefying GOD in all eternitie, which bleſſedneſſe is the joy of all Sainctes, and Elect, and will be motion eneugh vnto them, to rouſe and waken Gods children, for attending the LORD IESUS ſecond comming in the clowdes, and not to delay the tyme of their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance: but as for the ſecure man, who haſt not atteined vnto a ſenſe of this joy, neither knoweſt thou what this meaneth, it ſhall bee little helpe vnto him, becauſe hee is ſleeping in ſenſeleſſe ſecuritie, hee may well dreame of theſe joyes, but he hath no benefite of them, becauſe hee accounteth more of worldly things, and hath a benum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb facs="tcp:6606:35"/>
conſcience, that he hath eyes and ſees not, eares and heares not, a heart and yet can not vnderſtand.</p>
            <p>Hee is like <hi>Adam</hi> new made, ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before GOD, created with his whole members, and yet hath no vſe of them, vntill the LORD breath in a living ſoule &amp; ſpirit in him, then ſhall he be brought to conceaue of ſpirituall things, and ſo conſequently to this repentance.</p>
            <p>Yet I hope there is none ſo voide of knowledge, albeit vnregenerate, but hee ſhall bee driven to learne and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider with himſelfe, either by the law and order of nature, or by the law of conſcience: this one object eſpecially, the end of his being or creation, which I think there is no man, albeit he would forget GOD, and not once dreame of him, yet hee will haue a regard of him ſelfe, and ſeing hee findeth himſelfe to haue a being and life, for if it had pleaſed <hi>God</hi> thou hadſt not beene at all, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſeing thy being and life is not with the beaſtes, vnreaſonable; but ſuch a
<pb facs="tcp:6606:36"/>
reaſonable life and ſoule, as that thou conſidereſt that all other things, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever in the world created, Sunne, Moone, ſtarres, elements, tree, hearb, beaſts, and everie living creature, are all ſubject, and made for thy ſervice, therefore thou canſt not but conclude, albeit thou hadſt no other teachers, as the light of nature or the light of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, but that the end of thine owne creation muſt bee to ſerue GOD, the only Maker, moover, and governour of all thinges: and ſo having conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red that thou haſt a GOD and Maſter to ſerue, thou canſt not haue ſuch a baſe eſtimation, but that thou muſt giue account of thy ſervice, and the good ſervant will often meditate the day and tyme of account in his Maſters abſence, and will calculate and preaſe with all diligence to haue his count cleare a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his Maſters comming, eſpecially not knowing the tyme of his comming: which conſideration, albeit thou werſt an Athieſt, thou ſhall bee driven vnto
<pb facs="tcp:6606:36"/>
it, either by the light of nature, or light of conſcience: but deare Brother wee are more abundantly taught, as by theſe eſpecially in this our age, who are borne vnder the Ghoſpell of IESUS CHRIST, which great mercie of GOD towards vs is vnexpreſſible.</p>
            <p>Art thou therefore a man into whoſe heart this mercie is not as yet impreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed? and that thou haſt not regarded nor conſidered, what GOD hath lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned thee out of his Word, nor doſt not marke how GOD this long tyme bygone hath ſtand knocking with the hammers and trumpets of his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vangell, at the doore of thy ſoule, ſo that thou reſembleſt no more a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian, yet I pray thee reſemble the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then heerein, and let either thy owne conſcience tell thee, or the law of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture teach thee, that all things ſerveth for thy vſe and ſervice; and ſo conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently thou for the vſe of GOD, and to his ſervice: that is, either for a veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel of his glory in the Heavens for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver,
<pb facs="tcp:6606:37"/>
or for a ſpectacle of his juſtice in the paines and torments of hell for ever; and that thou muſt make account of thy actions at the great day of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count. Wilt thou neither imitate Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian nor Heathen heerein? not letting teach thee by the Word of GOD, law of nature, or light of conſcience, yet reject not feare with the vnreaſonable beaſt, for all beaſts whatſomever haue a kynd of feare, and will avoide (if they can) any paine or torment, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore haue ſome feare of thy ſelfe, els what ſhall become of thee heereafter at death: and if thou reject not this feare, yet thou ſhall bee brought ſo farre as to conſider the end of thy be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and creation, which is to ſerue GOD, and which ſervice thou muſt make ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of one day, that is, at the day of judgement, which albeit it ſhould bee prolonged ſome hundreth yeares, yet wee ſee by dayly experience, how death without exception, and exſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation of many, doeth violently com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell
<pb facs="tcp:6606:37"/>
all eſtates, young and old vnto this account, ſo that no man is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of the end of his lyfe.</p>
            <p>But what ſhall I ſay, this death is ſo commoun, little feared, and nothing regarded; alſo that worldly men pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe vnto them ſelues length of dayes, and tyme of repentance before death come. The young man in reſpect of his youth and abilitie will dreame of a long lyfe, and yet often cutte off be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore hee expect. The old man going in the brinck of his graue, doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſe himſelfe no ſuddaine death, and the tyme of his repentance to come ſoone eneugh, in reſpect GOD is mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull, and yet, before that ever hee exſpect, hee is ſo choaked, and cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beſet, and invironed lykewayes with the pangues of death, that in no man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of way once is hee able to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate vpon repentance, in reſpect of the ſuddaine ſorrowes, and of the cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ell paſſions of death, which mightily ever-whelmeth the whole bodie of
<pb facs="tcp:6606:38"/>
him in an eye blink: yea, in a verie moment of tyme, and dryveth the ſoule by violence out of the bodie, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Maker thereof, and there for to render account of its doings, whether it hath beene good or evill: and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore O Chriſtian, ſeing that repentance is ſuch a pretious jewell, ſtudie by all meanes to <hi>worke out thy ſalvation in feare and in trembling.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And yet the worldly man: I ſay not only the worldly man, but when I looke and conſider the doings of men, that the whole world for the greateſt part are ſleeping in ſuch ſenſeleſſe ſecurity, that they are rather dreaming with the Athieſt of no death, and if death, yet no reſurrection, no judgement no paine, no torment, no bleſſe, nor end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe joy vnto themſelues, and leading ſuch a negligent and careleſſe life; that I am aſſured they doe not once thinke of the laſt day, much leſſe of any ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coumpt to make of their doings at the day of judgment: But I will aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb facs="tcp:6606:38"/>
thee that the day of the LORD is comming, to rander everie man accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to his workes: Well, thou may ſleepe ſecure in the boſome of world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vanities, ſuch a ſhort ſpace as thou canſt, but the day is at hand, when thou ſhall bee fearefully wakned with the trumpet of Angels, and troupes of Heaven, when thou ſhall bee in a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment metamorphoſed from a mortall creature, into an never and ever dying veſſell, and ſpectacle of GODS wrath, where thou ſhalt ſtand naked in the ſight of all creatures, when as thy do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings neglegence and ſecure life, with all thy ſinnes that thou ſmall accoumpt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of before, ſhall bee raiſed as moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines in the view and preſence of thy conſcience, and ſhall beare witneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee: yea, ſhall overwhelme thee with endleſſe ſorrows in the bot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomleſſe pit of deſpare, and gulfe of Hell, where they ſhall torment thee for ever: thou being forſaken, and put out of the preſence of GOD, as a woe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb facs="tcp:6606:39"/>
reprobat, ſubject vnto deviliſh tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments: For if nothing moue thee, yet let feare moue thee, and haſt thou ſo much as feare of thy ſelfe, with the vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable beaſts? then feare GOD, feare his Majeſtie, feare his infinite power and juſtice, and repent and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend thy life, without the which thou canſt not be fred from helliſh torments.</p>
            <p>Wilt thou not feare GOD! yet feare becauſe of the Devill, in that hee is appointed for a tormenter of all vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitents, feare Hell, feare never dying paine and torment, feare the devils ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, and thou ſhall be brought at laſt to ſome practiſe of repentance: Art thou ſo farre come that thou art affraied of thy ſelfe, it is ſomething, I pray thee then, let this feare moue thee ſo farre, as to heare diligently GODS Word, partake the ſacraments, vſe the meanes of grace, pray to GOD albeit thy prayer bee imperfite, and but lip labour, lye and waite at the poole of <hi>Betheſda:</hi> which will, and obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence
<pb facs="tcp:6606:39"/>
of thy ſelfe, this feare may worke in thee, and yet thou being a vnrege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerat man, it can helpe nothing in the inward worke of this repentance, but yet art thou thus well exerciſed: Now in the tyme of grace, and lying at the poole of <hi>Betheſda,</hi> and gates of grace. Haſt thou attained ſo much as a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of this repentance; then I am aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured the LORD ſhall pittie thy hard caſe, and the Angel ſhall come downe and moue the watter, and thou ſhall bee waſhen from thy ſinne and leproſie.</p>
            <p>Wilt thou thus thruſt thy ſelfe in where CHRIST is, and thirſt after this repentance, then aſſuredly ſome tyme there ſhall goe one vertue or other from him, which ſhall alter and change thy hard heart into an heart of waxe, ſo that it ſhall melt with the ſorrowfull teares of repentance, and CHRIST ſhall giue them of the Well of the water of lyfe freely, who thirſteth after it, which when thou haſt a teined vnto a kynd of repentance, then marke well
<pb facs="tcp:6606:40"/>
it bee this, which briefly hath theſe infallible tokens, and methode in it ſelfe, true and ſanctified repentance indeede, that is, (I ſay) after a ſenſible ſight and confeſſion of thy ſinne, thou art accompanied with the teares of true repentance, out of a contrite and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken heart, where thou doſt reape faith in the mercies of GOD the Father, through IESUS CHRIST, and joy in the holy GHOST, budding foorth in the fruites of a godly lyfe, and holie converſation, theſe are infallible tokens of the true children of GOD, and are ſo faſt linked together, that they can not bee ſeparated from others.</p>
            <p>Art thou therefore vnregenerate, yet ſleeping in dead ſecuritie? Haſt thou not gotten a ſight and ſenſe of thy ſin? Thy cace is fearefull, <hi>for the Kingdome of Heaven is at hand,</hi> when the divell ſhall lay all thy ſins before thee, where thou ſhall bee wakned with a fearefull and terrible ſight of thy miſerie.</p>
            <p>Haſt thou not as yet confeſſed thy
<pb facs="tcp:6606:40"/>
ſinnes in private before thy GOD, and accuſed thy ſelfe of thy tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions? thy eſtate is to bee pittied, the day of the LORD is at hand, when thou muſt confeſſe them publicklie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thy will, where the Devill ſhall accuſe thee: yea, thy owne conſcience ſhall tell thee that thou art juſtly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned and caſt away for ever.</p>
            <p>Haſt thou not ſorrowed with the teares of true repentance? The tyme is at hand, when thou ſhall with a deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate ſorrow ſo lament and bewaile thy miſerable eſtate, that thou ſhall never bee comforted out of thy end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe miſerie, and never dying paine.</p>
            <p>Haſt not thine heart as yet concea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved a certaine joy in the holy GHOST, and faith of the mercies of GOD in his Sonne CHRIST IESUS: then O poore ſoule, and catiue creature, albeit thou wert a Monarch, and hade the riches of <hi>Croeſus,</hi> yet thy cace is moſt miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and lamentable: then I ſay O de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſperate creature, I pray thee delay not
<pb facs="tcp:6606:41"/>
the tyme of thy repentance, but goe and ſell all that thou poſeſſeſt, for this precious Iewell, and arlepennie of thy ſalvation, for the day of the LORD is at hand, when thou ſhall bee ſhut out of that endleſſe joy and reſt for ever, and then ſhall reape no faith in the mercies of GOD; but ſuch a doolefull and miſerable deſperation out of the juſtice of GOD, that thou ſhalt curſe the verie day of thy birth and nativitie.</p>
            <p>Haſt thou not hated the Devill and thy ſinne heere in this life, the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heaven is at hand, when as the Divell and thy ſinne, ſhall ſo hate thee with a perpetuall hatred, and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment thee in the Hell for ever.</p>
            <p>Haſt thou not kythed heere in this lyfe, the fruites of true repentance, in glorifying GOD, and in charitable and mercifull workes vnto thy brethren, I will aſſure thee, <hi>the Kingdome of Heaven is at hand,</hi> when as God ſhall be glorified in thy endleſſe ruyne and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, where no mercie nor chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie ſhall bee kythed on thee, but moſt
<pb facs="tcp:6606:41"/>
horrible and tyrannous torments exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted by the Devill and his Angels: O miſerie of all miſeries! O paine of all paines<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and never dying torments, how horrible and fearefull is thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memberance? Oh Father <hi>Abraham,</hi> who in thy lifetime was a paterne of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and pittie, on the poore and indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent, how art thou thus diſpoſed, as not to pittie the poore catiue, and tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented <hi>Dives</hi> in Hell fire, and ſend <hi>Lazarus</hi> vnto him, that hee may dip the top of his finger in water to coole his tongue, in ſuch fire and vnquench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able flame? or how doeſt thou not com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort him in his miſerie, that it ſhall either end from him, or hee from it, which would haue giuen this poore damned and tormented <hi>Dives</hi> ſome contentment: but I ſee thou doſt ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther rejoyce as to haue pitie in that it tendeth vnto the glorie and juſtice of GOD, and that his paine is end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, and never ſhall bee eaſed, how terrible ſhould the conſideration bee vnto a good Chriſtian of the ſtraitneſſe
<pb facs="tcp:6606:42"/>
of this torments, and perpetuitie of paine for ever.</p>
            <p>But on the contrare, art thou a ſoule who haſt repented of thy former tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, and doſt repent dayly of thy infirmities, who haſt attained vnto this ſanctified ſorrow, out of the which thou haſt conceaved the hony of true repentance, namely joy in the holy GHOST, faith in the mercies of GOD in his Sonne CHRIST IESUS, it is a certaine token thou art a child of God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the Kingdome of Heaven, which thy ſoule thirſteth after is at hand, where thou ſhalt injoy that fulneſſe and ſumme of all bleſſed joy, with all the Sainctes and Angels in the Heavens for ever: which glorious, bleſſed, and everlaſting Kingdome of GOD is ſo furniſhed with joyes, that no creature in Heaven nor in earth can thinke of, much leſſe expreſſe this eternall happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe layed vp in ſtore for the elect, where the juſt ſhall ſhine like the Sun, <hi>Math.</hi> 15. This is the promiſed crowne
<pb facs="tcp:6606:42"/>
of glory, this is the Paradice and place of pleaſure, and joy of all Saincts, this is the hidden Manna which no man knoweth, but hee who injoyeth it, and with DAVID, Happie are they that liue in thy houſe O LORD, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8. 3. for they ſhall bee drunke with the river of GODS divine pleaſures, and with the abundance of GODS houſe, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 3.5. where wee ſhall ſee GOD which is our chiefe happineſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeaking of this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, ſayeth, O joy aboue all joyes, paſſing all joyes, and without which there is no joy: when ſhall I enter in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to thee, when ſhall I injoy thee, to ſee my GOD that dwelleth in thee? O everlaſting Kingdome! O Kingdome of all eternities! O light without end! O peace of GOD, that paſſeth all vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, in which the ſoules of the Saincts doe reſt with thee! O King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of everlaſting bleſſe, where thou O LORD the hope of all Sancts art, and the diademe of their perpetuall
<pb facs="tcp:6606:43"/>
glory, rejoycing them on everie ſide, with thy bleſſed ſight: In this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome there is infinite joy, mirth with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out ſadneſſe, health without ſorrow, life without labour, light without dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, felicitie without abaitment, all goodneſſe without evill, where youth flooriſheth that never waxeth old: life that knoweth no end, beautie that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver fadeth, loue that never cooleth, health that never diminiſheth, joy that never ceaſeth, where ſorrow is never felt, complaint is never heard, matter of ſadneſſe is never ſeene, nor evill ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe is never feared for that they poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe thee O LORD, which art the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection of their felicitie.</p>
            <p>Oh deare brother into this verie moment of life, whereon dependeth all eternitie, why ſhould wee delay our repentance, when I looke vnto the world with my ſpirituall eyes, I won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to ſee how the moſt part of men, wearie themſelues in vanitie, and in the triffle of worldly things, neglecting
<pb facs="tcp:6606:43"/>
this Heavenly treaſure and Kingdome of all happineſſe: why doth not rather now all men, in the laſt moment of tymes, runne after this Kingdome in buying this pure and tryed gold of CHRIST IESUS: It is a lamentable and inward griefe of true Chriſtians, to ſee almoſt the whole world ſo buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and exerciſed in buying ſtraw in <hi>Egypt,</hi> where as they could buy fine gold with leſſe labour, and at a lower pryce: is it not now tyme for worldly men, to follow the doctrine of CHRIST, and ſell all that ever they haue to pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe this Kingdome? and the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of <hi>Paul,</hi> who eſteemed all the world as dung, in reſpect of this Iewell, and <hi>Ignatius,</hi> who ſaith, fire, gallows, beaſtes, breaking of my bones, quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tring of my members, cruſhing of my bodie, all the torments of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill together, let them come vpon me ſo I may injoy this treaſure of Heaven: and <hi>Auguſtine</hi> who was content to ſuffer torments everie day, yea the
<pb facs="tcp:6606:44"/>
verie torments of Hell it ſelfe to haue this joy.</p>
            <p>Oh how few conſidreth this King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heaven to bee at hand, and how many are they who beſtow their tyme in vanitie, pleaſures, and delyts of the world, ſo that men all moſt are bent to wickedneſſe, and abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, which is an infallible token, that deſtruction is imminent, and the Kingdome of Heaven is at hand: and ſeing all tokens and prophecies are ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filed in the Scripture, whereby it is moſt certaine that the day of the LORD is at hand, ſo is the hardneſſe of the heart and wickedneſſe of mankynde likewiſe a true token and a note of imminent deſtruction, as is evident by all examples of the holy Scripture, how it hath beene the forme of worldlings and reprobate perſons to harden their hearts, and double their ſinnes againſt the day of vengeance: So was it in the dayes of <hi>Sodome</hi> &amp; <hi>Gomorrah,</hi> who could not bee warned of <hi>Lots</hi> exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations,
<pb facs="tcp:6606:44"/>
but hardned their hearts and doubled their iniquities: <hi>Iudas</hi> wicked reſolution could not bee changed by his maſters forewarning preſently be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his imminent deſtruction, neither the Iewes would take heede vnto all the prophecies, or plagues hanging o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them, but hardned their hearts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt all exhortations, preachings, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, and thundrings made by Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, proceeding in ſuch an exceſſe in ſinne, and defection from GOD, hard before their vtter ruine, and deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on executed by <hi>Titus.</hi> And when we conferre to theſe former examples, thoſe of our dayes and latter times how mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifully and abundantlie is GOD warn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and crying vs to repentance and amendement of life, by faithfull Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of his Ghoſpell.</p>
            <p>But who heareth and repenteth, where is the worldly and avaritious man, who hath amended his life, and turned from his avarice, or where is the prodigall man who hath left his
<pb facs="tcp:6606:45"/>
prodigalitie, and is clothing the nak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and feeding the hungrie, or where is the proud and ambitious man, who is become humble and lowlie, or where is the falſe vſurer and deceatfull man reſtoring it againe vnto the poore with <hi>Zacheus</hi> in the Ghoſpell: but rather all ſinnes are prevailing in their high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt degrees, drunkenneſſe, adulterie, pryde and avarice, eſpecially are become ſo vſuall and followed of all men that they are rather accoumpted vertue than vice: ſo that the Elect of this age may now ſigh and cry out with that holy Martyre <hi>Policarpus, O Domine in quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam tempora nos reſervaſti:</hi> O LORD what perrilous, ſorrowfull, and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable times letteſt thou thy Elect liue in thoſe dayes, what tyme or age in the world, ſince the creation of <hi>Adam,</hi> hath more ſinne and wickedneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounded, or what time hath there beene in old, whereinto charitie and trueth hath beene ſo cold, and wholly depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from the hearts of men, as now
<pb facs="tcp:6606:45"/>
in thoſe dayes: and if the ground of election were not ſure, what a hard thing is it, and a matter of great dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficultie for a Chriſtian ſoule, to attaine vnto the worke of his calling, and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevere in true faith and obedience, into thoſe dangerous and latter times: ſeeing how rare they are to bee found, who by a godly life and converſation, ſheweth a good example to others, and the Devill hath got ſuch victory in this age, that he hath almoſt all do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions, and powers of the world vnder him, as Ambaſſadours: yea, moſt of all creatures, are verie inſtruments for inlarging the Kingdome of Sathan, who certainly goeth about like a roa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring Lyon, ſeeking whom hee may devoure: ſeing hee feareth his helliſh torments draweth ſoone to a begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and therefore ſtriveth with all diligence, if it were poſſible, to lead and carie all ſoules borne on the earth vnto endleſſe perdition, and deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with him: will wee looke vnto
<pb facs="tcp:6606:46"/>
all the eſtates of men, both ciuill and ecleſiaſticall, from the rich Monarch vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the poore beggar, from the learned doctor and prelate, vnto the loweſt deacon, from the aged father, vnto the verie infant, wee ſhall ſee now in thoſe dayes the hearts of Kings mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and induced more by Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dours of Sathan, than by the counſell of the godly, imbracing rather the counſell of ſubtill and treacherous <hi>Achi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tophell,</hi> who ſtandeth after the deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and ruine of a Commonwell, than the counſell of the old &amp; wiſe favourer of land and policie, and that in thoſe laſt times. How pittifull a thing it is to ſee ſuch a conſort of traitours to intrude themſelues in the companie of potentats and ſuperior eſtates, who by their deceiving prctaickes haue brought to paſſe ſuch fearefull events, in whole <hi>Europ,</hi> as miſerable experience by loſſe of life, wife, children and goods, hath proued vnto many thouſands, within thoſe few yeares begone: Behold how
<pb facs="tcp:6606:46"/>
nobles and men of State, how their hearts and eares are locked vp from the cryes of the poore, and repell their cryes without helpe, as the ſtony rockes repelleth the vaves of the Sea without ſence: looke vnto the lower eſtate of men, thou ſhalt finde nothing more to abound than pryde, in imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tating the footſteps and forme of appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell of noble men, luſt of the fleſh, in abuſing the Temples of the holie Ghoſt with inceſt, adulterie, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nication: drunkenneſſe in ſpending of their owne life and meanes; behold the verie beggars, who as men would ſay, in troubles, in neceſſities, and want ſhould worke and ſeeke that everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing riches in the LORD, waiting for the comming of the LORD IESUS; thou ſhall marke no hungring nor thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting after righteouſneſſe in them, but a maine conſort of ignorance, lewde and vitious creatures, who are more exerciſed and buſied in time of divyne ſervice in tipling and ſecret places, and
<pb facs="tcp:6606:47"/>
about their owne bodies, rather as to finde them in GODS houſe begging grace vnto their ſoules: will we looke vnto the common courſe of youth, thou ſhalt finde and heare the firſt leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon they learne, is pryde, curſing, and prophaning of GODS Name, even from their verie infancie: againe from their youth to their age, running from one vice to another, and where then wee ſee commonly they are more ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted vnto the worlds avaritiouſneſſe. and lewdneſſe, than with any godlineſſe, or goodneſſe, and ſo moſt part ending their dayes without repentance, they die miſerablie without any ſence of their ſinnes, and are ſwallowed vp at the houre of death into the horrible pit of deſpare, where their torments doe beginne with never dying paine. Behold the Eccleſiaſticall government, thou ſhall ſee avarice and ambition ſo to haue intruded themſelues amongſt many of them, ſo that they ſeeme ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to digge earthly than heavenlie
<pb facs="tcp:6606:47"/>
treaſures, reſembling well the worke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of <hi>Noah,</hi> who were good biggers, but not poſſeſſers: ſo that many Kirk<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men are good edifiers in the word, but are evill example givers: who are ſo poſſeſſed, part with ambition, and other with avaritiouſneſſe of the world, that they ſeeme to neglect their owne ſalvation. Farre bee it ſaid from the worthie Divine, and faithfull Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Ghoſpell, who ſeeketh not their owne glory and advancement, but the advancement of GODS glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, and edifying of ſoules vnto GOD, all which ſpait of iniquitie, and ſenſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe ſecuritie, are evident tokens I ſay of imminent ruine and deſtruction: for this our age liveth as ſecure of our ſelues, as in the dayes of <hi>Noah, Sodom,</hi> and <hi>Gomorrha,</hi> and as the <hi>Iewes</hi> before the deſtruction of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> but how came it to paſſe in theſe dayes, when they were moſt ſure, and expected leaſt any deſtruction, preſentlie the flouds of Heaven opened, and the waters o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verflowed
<pb facs="tcp:6606:48"/>
the whole earth with her creatures; the elements conjoyned them ſelues in fire and brimſtone, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Gomorrha:</hi> and when the <hi>Iewes</hi> cuppe of abhomination was full, GOD ſtirred vp inſtruments amongſt themſelues, who preſentlie were the cauſe of their owne deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction in <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and the whole land of <hi>Iudea.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It is to bee feared therefore, that it will likewiſe ſo event in theſe laſt dayes, when all ſinne taketh the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per hand, and when men liue moſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gligently, and careleſſe of themſelues, that then the LORD IESUS will come in the clowdes, and take account of the wickedneſſe of mankynd.</p>
            <p>The wicked abhomination of mans heart, made GOD in his wrath cry out, and ſay, <hi>I repent that ever I made man, Geneſ.</hi> 6.6. And certainly, if we will view and conſider now in thoſe tymes the tragedie of the world, it is placed in verie wickedneſſe it ſelfe, and when
<pb facs="tcp:6606:48"/>
wee looke vnto conſcience of religion, how many wonderous curſed and dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned ſects and opinions are ſpred on the faee of the earth, and everie man affirming Scripture for vpholding their hereticall opinion, wreſting the Word of GOD vnto their owne willes and inventions: O thou religion! how art thou changed and diſfigured, yea, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther abuſed, how can the ſimple ſoule knew thee, or to what hand ſhall hee turne, when ſo many miſerable opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are at ſtrife, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. It is onelie the humble heart that the trueth is manifeſted vnto: it is not without cauſe that the ſpirit of GOD prophecieth in the <hi>Revelation,</hi> that thou ſhouldeſt bee <hi>clothed in ſackcloth, Revel.</hi> 11. yea thou art ſurelie diſguyſed, and moſt by the great comfort of Antichriſtians, who are diſperſed amongſt all Nations.</p>
            <p>Now is the mother of whoredome mounted vpon the ſeven headed beaſt, that ten horned monſter, yea that old Dragon the devill hath given him
<pb facs="tcp:6606:49"/>
his power, and hath printed on his fore head the name of blaſphemie, he ſpueth out now a dayes vncleane ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, who are ambaſſadours to inlarge the Kingdome of Sathan: ſo that the Church may now lament in the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Ieremiah: Haue you no regard, all yee that paſſe by this way, behold and ſee if there bee any ſorrow like vnto my ſorrow,</hi> and that GOD is forced now to ſpeake, <hi>I haue long tyme holden my peace, I haue beene ſtill and refrained my ſelfe, now will I cry like a trawel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing woman, and I ſhall deſtroy and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voure both at once.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O wicked and abhominable age! O ſinfull and miſerable generation! what other object doſt thou bring before our eyes, but ſinne and wickedneſſe: are not Kings oppoſed againſt Kings, and Nation againſt Nation, ſo that the one triumpheth over other mens ſpoile: yea, ſubjects mutine againſt their owne naturall Prince, and all ſinnes &amp; wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe are conquerours, and drunken in
<pb facs="tcp:6606:49"/>
by men as water of a thirſtie ſtomacke: what lying and deceiving, what ſlan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and ſhameleſſe villanie, is done by all the eſtates of men in all places, the generall voice of the people is nothing els, but vanitie, baudrie, whooring, detraction, and backbyting, pryde, en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy, deceit, drunkenneſſe diſſimulation, wantonneſſe, flatterie, lying, ſwearing, perjuring and blaſpheming, ſo that all abhomination and wickedneſſe is growne to a certaine perfection and maturitie in thoſe dayes, and that the ſhoulders of this vniverſall globe, is o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaiden with the wickedneſſe of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynde: The trumpets of GOD may now cry out with the Prophet <hi>Ieremiah, O yee Heavens, bee aſtonied at this: bee afraide and vtterly confounded, ſaith the LORD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And laſtly, will wee looke vnto GODS creatures and vnto the elements, what comets, ſignes, and wonderous tokens hath beene ſeene, and heard within thoſe few yeares, I doubt not
<pb facs="tcp:6606:50"/>
but it is well knowne vnto the dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent ſearcher, as experience hath well taught, albeit not to all in thoſe parts, yet in ſundrie parts in <hi>Germanie, Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lie, Denmarke,</hi> and <hi>Norvay,</hi> are kythed fearefull tokens, as vntimely birth, and Monſters borne in <hi>Denmarke,</hi> blood rained from the Heavens on the earth one halfe foote deepe, aſhe, ſtones, and fire rained from the Heavens in <hi>Iſland,</hi> the pittifull crying thryſe of a chylde in the mothers wombe in <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rone</hi> in <hi>Norvay.</hi> All which I haue ſeene approved and heard by expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience, and many more viſions, and terrible tokens ſeene in <hi>Europ,</hi> both by earthquakes, overflowing of watters, and fearefull viſions ſeene and heard in the elements, and witneſſed by ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drie: all ſuch things may verie well teach vs that the latter dayes are im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent: Therefore <hi>hee that is vnjuſt let him bee vnjuſt still,</hi> (ſaith CHRIST) <hi>Revel.</hi> 22. let the wicked man dwell in his abhominations, and triumph in
<pb facs="tcp:6606:50"/>
all kynde of wickedneſſe, for beholde (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>I come ſhortly, and my reward is with mee, to render everie man according to his workes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O would to GOD wee could con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider attentiuelie the proſpect of all GODS creatures, how they teach vs dayly, that all things draweth to their end, all things waxe worſe and briefer, the earth giveth not her wonted fruits but worſe: men ſinneth with new ſinnes, GOD plagueth againe with new ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and the life of man commonly attaineth not vnto former and wonted age, and commonly cut off in her firſt prime, the waters giue not their won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted aboundance of creatures: the ſunne and Moone miſſeth their wonted ſhine, and vertues, the ſtarres of Heaven are, turned into comets, for preaching of GODS vengeance: the Aire and all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lements are moved with fearefull and vnacquainted tempeſtuousſtormes, and all thinges as it were wiſh to bee diſolved, ſo that the earth is waerie,
<pb facs="tcp:6606:51"/>
worne, and overburdened with the wickedneſſe of her creatures, alſo that ſhee fainteth, trembleth, and wiſheth to bee fred, and disburthened of her moſt vntolerable birth, all which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phecies fulfilled, and conferred together with the experience of this our age, there is no ſpirituall man, but of neceſſitie muſt conclude, that the day of the LORD is at hand: and if any learned Divines haue ought to pretend, as yet not fulfilled, yet I perſwade my ſelfe there is none of them, but will ſubſcryue to CHRISTS owne words, that <hi>the latter tymes ſhall bee ſhortned for the Elects ſake. Math.</hi> 24. and that all the Saints in Heaven are now re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joycing, and hoping for the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the fulneſſe of their joy, when that ſoule and bodie may be coupled and vnited together, and enter with all the bleſſed Elect into that glorious and triumphant Church, and Kingdome of glory.</p>
            <p>Therefore to conclude, I ſay, Will
<pb facs="tcp:6606:51"/>
nothing moue thee vnto this repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, no the mercies, patience, and long ſuffering of GOD can moue the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>? neither the benefites, and temporall bleſſings of GOD beſtowed vpon thee; nor the proſpect and defection of ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and creatures, neither the ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>homination and wickedneſſe of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynd; no not the dayly experience of violent death can moue thee; yet let the feare of imminent juſtice and day of the LORD, that glorious Kingdome of Heaven now at hand moue thee to repentance, and amendement of life, I pray thee conſider with thy ſelfe, if there bee any creature created in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven or in earth, who can by any evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent argument aſſure thee, that when thou ſitteſt downe to thy table, that thou ſhall ryſe before CHRIST come in the clowdes, and aske account of thee: or when thou goeſt out of thy doores about thy worldly reſpectes, to turne back to thine houſe, but that thou may be caught into the clowdes
<pb facs="tcp:6606:52"/>
of Heaven, before the juſtice ſeate of GOD, either when thou lyeſt downe in thy bed with thy mortall bodie, but that thou ſhall be in an eye blinck in thy ſleepe exchanged, into an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortall creature, and preſentlie preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted before the glorious throne, and Majeſtie of CHRIST IESUS, to giue account of thy workes.</p>
            <p>Good LORD! when I doe meditate with my ſelfe of the imminencie of this Kingdome of Heaven, and of the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer workes of mankynd in this age, it troubleth my thoughts, and vnquy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eteth my ſpirits, and maketh my bones to quake, and my fleſh to tremble for feare, to thinke how that the LORD of Glory ſhall find the whole world in ſuch damnable and pitiefull eſtate, and how few they are who are prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red with the oyle of grace in the lampes of their heartes: ſhall hee not rather find men buſied about the vanities of the world, and luſtes of the fleſh, then attending the comming of the LORD
<pb facs="tcp:6606:52"/>
IESUS: O doolefull and miſerable ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience! O wicked abhomination and ſinfull generation of mankynd! What fearefull juſtice art thou prophecying to bee imminent. Oh how doolefull, lamentable, and ſorrowfull will the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent proue to many, who are ſleeping in ſenceleſſe ſecuritie in the lap of world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vanities: awaken O ſecure man, and harden not thy heart, nor delay not the tyme of thy repentance, abuſe not the long patience and ſuffering of GOD, accept of grace in this verie laſt mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of grace, for now the Kingdome of Heaven is at hand, where the gates of grace and mercie ſhall bee cloſed, and never opened nor offered againe. O miſerable, wretched, damned, and forlorne creature art thou, if thou re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent not in time, how pittifull ſhall then thy eſtate bee, when thou ſhall bee forced with perpetuall ſhame, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>famie, and confuſion, to ſtand naked in the preſence of all creatures, and before the juſtice throne of GOD,
<pb facs="tcp:6606:53"/>
where thou ſhalt heare that horrible ſentence, of the KING of all Kings, and judge of all the whole world, <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from mee yee workers of iniquitie, into everlaſting fire prepared for the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill and his angels.</hi> O terrible and fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſentence once pronunced, how fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and vnexpreſſible ſhall thy paine bee, where no repentance, no teares, no treaſures, no friend, no foe, no griefe, no ſorrow, will then helpe thy miſerable, damnable, &amp; deſperate ſoule, out of her endleſſe quaill, and never conſuming torments. And on the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trare, how joyfull ſhall that ſoule bee who hath repented heere in this life, when they ſhall bee promoted in the Heavens, to liue as Kings in that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlaſting happineſſe and joye of all Saincts. The LORD of his mercie make vs prepared againſt the comming of the LORD IESUS, to whom with the Father and holy Ghoſt, be praiſe and glory for ever. AMEN.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:6606:53"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
